Mss.Rec.19 Mss.Rec.19
American Philosophical Society
Recordings at Yakutat, Alaska
1952
Mss.Rec.19
American Philosophical Society
7.0 Reel(s)
Recorded by Frederica de Laguna in the field at Yakutat, Alaska in 1952. Contains various types of Tlingit songs, including mourning songs, drinking songs, love songs, personal songs, and 3 Athabaskan songs, most likely Southern Tutchone. Includes Raven and other stories with some translations.
7 sound tape reels (4 hr., 9 min.): analog, 7 1/2 ips, half track, mono; 7 in. Notes, 30 p. The collection was re-boxed and re-labeled due to the poor quality of the original boxes. The sound quality of the collection is excellent, with a minimum of distortion and background noise.
De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004
Johnson, Minnie
Reed, Jack
White, Charley
White, Jenny
Related Archival Materials
See also Frederica de Laguna, Tlingit and Yakutat Songs (Rec. 30).
Conditions Governing Access
Permission required for access to materials. Please consult the Manuscripts Librarian for details.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donor, Frederica de Laguna, 1959.
Children's songs; Indians of North America--Alaska; Lituya Bay (Alaska); Mourning customs--United States--Alaska; Raven (Legendary character)--Legends; Sea otter--Folklore; Sound recordings; Speeches, addresses, etc.; Thunderbird (Legendary character)--Legends; Tlingit Indians--Folklore; Tlingit Indians--Music; Tlingit mythology
- Audio recordings
  - Mourning song, 1952-06-20; 01-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:05:23; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Reed, Jack
    Scope and Contents note
    "1. Introductory remarks in broken English by Jack Reed of the song he is going to sing. 1:40 minutes. Whistle at 1:46. 2. Mourning song, compossed by Dry Bay Chief George, and sung by Jack Reed. There is a pause from 1:55 to 2:37, before Jack Reed begins singing. The song, followed by a few remakrs in Tlingit, lasts from 2:37 to 4:35 minutes. Whislte at 4:35. Break and pause to 5:05 minutes. 3. Identification of the above by F. de Laguna, 5:05 to 5:25."
    Existence and Location of Originals note
    This file is a compressed, digitized version of the original. The APS Library maintains the original format (Sound tape reel) as well as an uncompressed digitized version of this recording.
    Indians of North America--Alaska; Mourning customs--United States--Alaska; Tlingit Indians--Alaska--Music; Tlingit language; Yakutat (Alaska)
  - Tlingit song, 1952-06-21; 01-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:27; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Reed, Jack
    Indians of North America--Alaska; Tlingit Indians--Alaska--Music; Tlingit language; Yakutat (Alaska)
  - How the Russians gave whiskey to Raven, 1952-06-21; 01-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:07:02; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Johnson, Minnie; Reed, Jack; White, Charley; White, Jenny
    "Charley White tells the story in Tlingit of how the Russians gave whiskey to Raven. ([Around 2:20 mark] his foot can be heard tapping.) Story lasts [approx. 4 minutes]. Without a break, Charley White, Jack Reed (who beats banjo with ruler wrapped in cloth as a drum), Jennie White and Minnie Johnson sing the song referring to the story, which was composed by Dry Bay Chief George. Song from [approx 4:00 to 6:30]. Final remarks by Charley White."
    Indians of North America--Alaska; Raven (Legendary character)--Legends; Tlingit Indians--Folklore; Tlingit language; Whiskey; Yakutat (Alaska)
  - Explanation in English of preceding story on how the Russians gave whiskey to Raven, 1952-06-21; 01-04; 1.0 .mp3; 00:07:08; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Johnson, Minnie
    Indians of North America--Alaska; Raven (Legendary character)--Legends; Russians--Alaska; Tlingit Indians--Folklore; Whiskey; Yakutat (Alaska)
  - How Raven deceived the Sea Otters in order to get medicine (plants) from them, 1952-06-21; 01-05; 1.0 .mp3; 00:06:14; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Johnson, Minnie; Reed, Jack; White, Charley; White, Jenny
    "Story lasts to 1:32, followed by song connected with the story, starting at 1:55. "Jack Reed (with banjo as drum), Charley White (who soon takes over as song leader), Jennie White and Minnie Johnson sing.... The song ends with the spoken words hutc eya ('that's all').... Final remarks by Charley White.... Identification of the two preceding songs by F. de Laguna." De Laguna's closing comments also summarize prior recording, APSdigrec_0594.
    Indians of North America--Alaska; Raven (Legendary character)--Legends; Sea otter--Folklore; Tlingit Indians--Medicine; Tlingit language; Yakutat (Alaska)
  - Story about the culture hero, qakeqw'tE, who taught the Athabaskans at Dry Bay to catch oelachens, 1952-07-04; 01-06; 1.0 .mp3; 00:17:59; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Johnson, Minnie; Reed, Jack
    "Story about the culture hero, qakeqw'tE, who taught the Athabaskans at Dry Bay how to catch oelachens.... Jack Reed sings the song composed by the hero of the story, when the grateful Athabaskans gave him a wife. It end with the spoken words hutc awa ('that's all'). Jack Reed resumes the story.... Explanation of the above story in English by Minnie Johnson."
    Athapascan Indians; Fishing; Indians of North America--Alaska; Tlingit Indians--Folklore; Yakutat (Alaska)
  - Speeches in Tlingit, 1952-07-04; 01-07; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:34; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Johnson, Minnie; McClellan, Catharine; Reed, Jack; Williams, Sarah
    Indians of North America--Alaska; Speeches, addresses, etc.; Tlingit language; Yakutat (Alaska)
  - Drinking Song, 1952-07-04; 01-08; 1.0 .mp3; 00:03:19; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Johnson, Minnie; Reed, Jack
    "Minnie Johnson says a few words.... Minnie Johnson sings drinking song, using the banjo as drum, but forgetting to hold down the strings... Whistle.... Jack Reed is urged to sing too, but refuses.... Minnie Johnson translates the song...."
    Drinking songs--Alaska; Indians of North America--Alaska; Tlingit Indians--Alaska--Music; Yakutat (Alaska)
  - Practice singing of Thunderbird Origin Song, 1952-07-30; 02-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:06:55; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Italio, Frank; Johnson, Annie; Johnson, Minnie
    "Prompted by F de Laguna, Minnie Johnson explains the machine to Frank Italio. Whistle at 1:04 minutes. Frank Italio starts to explain in Tlingit about gò.snA', the little boy who was lost and rescued by the Thunderbirds, when he is interrupted at 1:20 to 1:25 minutes by the entrance of Mrs. Annie Johnson. Begins singing mourning song for gosnA' at 2:30 minutes, and is interrupted by Minnie at 3:40 to 3:45 minutes. Ends singing at 4:22 minutes. Frank and Minnie and Annie talk. There is a reference to the Tlingit language; laughter at 5:00 minutes; reference to yatqwan XEnaX (old people's language); an argument from 6 to 6:30 minutes. At 6:50 Minnie Johnson tells F de Laguna 'Shut it off.' Machine is stopped." Frank Italio also identified as "CAnkukedi (or dakAstina) 'Thunderbird Clan.')"
    Arguments; Athapascan languages; Eyak language; Tlingit Indians--Alaska--Music; Tlingit language; Yakutat (Alaska)
  - Explanation of Thunderbird Origin Story; Mourning song for go.snA', 1952-07-30; 02-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:05:03; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Italio, Frank; Johnson, Minnie
    "Frank explains Thunderbird Origin Story in Tlingit. At [approx. 2:45] Minnie Johnson urges Frank Italio to sing. Mourning soung for go.snA' with rapid beat of cane." Correction made by collector on later recording that original identification of the language of the song--referred to as "yatqwan XEnaX (old people's language)"--was likely misidentified as Eyak and is instead likely to be "in some dialect of Athabaskan." Frank Italio also identified as "CAnkukedi (or dakAstina) 'Thunderbird Clan.')"
    Mourning customs--United States--Alaska; Thunderbird (Legendary character)--Legends; Tlingit Indians--Alaska--Music; Tlingit language; Tlingit mythology; Yakutat (Alaska)
  - Explanation of Mourning song for go.snA', 1952-07-30; 02-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:06:07; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Johnson, Minnie
    Alsek River; Mourning customs--United States--Alaska; Thunderbird (Legendary character)--Legends; Tlingit Indians--Alaska--Music; Tlingit language; Yakutat (Alaska)
  - Song for the Thunderbird Screen, 1952-07-30; 02-04; 1.0 .mp3; 00:02:58; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Italio, Frank; Johnson, Minnie
    "Minnie Johnson explains [that this song] was composed in Tlingit by go.snA', and sung by Frank Italio, q'At'axítci." Frank Italio also identified as "CAnkukedi (or dakAstina) 'Thunderbird Clan.')"
    Indians of North America--Alaska; Thunderbird (Legendary character)--Legends; Tlingit Indians--Alaska--Music; Tlingit mythology; Yakutat (Alaska)
  - Explanation of Song for Thunderbird Screen, 1952-07-30; 02-05; 1.0 .mp3; 00:03:34; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Johnson, Minnie
    "Minnie Johnson explains [that the preceding song] was composed in Tlingit by go.snA', and sung by Frank Italio, q'At'axítci."
  - Love song to Teqweydi's and Kagwantan's Children, 1952-07-30; 02-06; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:29; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Italio, Frank; Johnson, Minnie
    "This song was composed by Frank Italio. It is sung both by him and by Minnie Johnson. While singing and practicing, Frank became very jovial and held Minnie's hand in both of this. According to the unrecorded explanation, the song was originally composed in honor of Frank Italio's father, Kagwantan-yAdi, i.e. son of the Kagwantan, but the first verse was changed to make it a love song for Teqwedi's children, of whom Minnie herself is one." Frank Italio also identified as "CAnkukedi (or dakAstina) 'Thunderbird Clan.')"
    Children's songs; Indians of North America--Alaska; Tlingit Indians--Alaska--Music; Tlingit language; Yakutat (Alaska)
  - Explanation by F. de Laguna of the preceding songs and stories, 1952-07-30; 02-07; 1.0 .mp3; 00:03:18; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004
    "Correction is made that the language of the Thunderbird Origin Song...is probably in Athabaskan, not Eyak."
    Indians of North America--Alaska; Tlingit language; Yakutat (Alaska)
  - Continuation of Love Song, 1952-07-30; 02-08; 1.0 .mp3; 00:03:06; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Italio, Frank; Johnson, Minnie
    Frank Italio also identified as CAnkukedi (or dakAstina) 'Thunderbird Clan.'
  - Explanation in English of the Love Song, 1952-07-30; 02-09; 1.0 .mp3; 00:02:55; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Johnson, Minnie
    Children's songs; Indians of North America--Alaska; Tlingit Indians--Alaska--Music; Yakutat (Alaska)
  - Three Snatches of Mourning Song for Lituya Drowning, 1952-07-30; 02-10; 1.0 .mp3; 00:04:40; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Italio, Frank; Johnson, Minnie
    "This song was composed by a t'luq'naxAdi woman, wuck'ik'a, for her brothers who were drowned at Lituya Bay. It was sung by Frank Italio, but Minnie Johnson was too overcome by grief to translate. It was impossible to get Frank Italio to give a signal for turning on and off the machine so that the full song was not recoreded." Frank Italio also identified as "CAnkukedi (or dakAstina) 'Thunderbird Clan.')"
    Drowning; Indians of North America--Alaska; Mourning customs--United States--Alaska; Tlingit Indians--Alaska--Music; Tlingit language; Yakutat (Alaska)
  - Identification of recording, 1952-07-30; 02-11; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:47; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004
  - Farewell song to t'luq'naxAdi's daughters, 1952-08-13; 03-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:02:25; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Johnson, Annie
    Song composed by Annie Johnson's mother's brother, tánAXaci.
  - Explanation in English of Farewell song to t'luq'naxAdi's daughters, 1952-08-13; 03-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:02:12; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Johnson, Minnie
    Indians of North America--Alaska; Tlingit Indians--Alaska--Music; Yakutat (Alaska)
  - Song, composed by Raven and sung to Killerwhales, 1952-08-13; 03-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:00; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Johnson, Annie; Johnson, Minnie
    Indians of North America--Alaska; Raven (Legendary character); Tlingit Indians--Alaska--Music; Tlingit language; Yakutat (Alaska)
  - Story & Song about Averted Fight Between Tsimshian and Yakutat Natives, 1952-08-13; 03-04; 1.0 .mp3; 00:09:14; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Johnson, Annie; Johnson, Minnie
    Story told first in Tlingit by Annie Johnson, with interjections by Minnie Johnson, followed by song. Song composed by miniie Johnson's mother's brother, Ckinan.
    Hunting--Alaska; Indians of North America--Alaska--Hunting; Tlingit Indians--Alaska--History; Tlingit language; Tsimshian Indians--History; Yakutat (Alaska)
  - Explanation in English of Story & Song about Averted Fight Between Tsimshian and Yakutat Natives, 1952-08-13; 03-05; 1.0 .mp3; 00:10:31; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Johnson, Minnie
    Hunting--Alaska; Indians of North America--Alaska--Hunting; Tlingit Indians--Alaska--History; Tsimshian Indians--History; Yakutat (Alaska)
  - Three Athabaskan Songs belonging to the cAnkukedi, 1952-08-29; 04-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:03:41; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Italio, Frank; Johnson, Minnie
    "These are three of four songs in gonana (Athabaskan) given by the Aiyan Chief to the cAnkukedi because their people were drowned in the Aiyan River when going to visit him. There were originally four songs, but Frank Italio, who sang them, has forgotten the fourth."
    Athapascan Indians; Indians of North America--Alaska; Tlingit Indians--Alaska--Music; Tlingit language; Yakutat (Alaska)
  - Song in Tlingit about the Drowning in the Aiyan River, 1952-08-29; 04-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:06:06; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Italio, Frank; Johnson, Minnie
    Drowning; Indians of North America--Alaska; Tlingit Indians--Alaska--Music; Tlingit language; Yakutat (Alaska)
  - Raven Cycle, 1952-08-29; 04-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:23:38; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Italio, Frank; Johnson, Minnie
    Story resumed on APSdigrec_0627. See Related Recording.
    Indians of North America--Alaska; Raven (Legendary character)--Legends; Tlingit Indians--Folklore; Tlingit language; Tlingit mythology; Yakutat (Alaska)
  - Pet Song for Harold Gray, 1952-09-09; 05-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:04:04; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Johnson, Minnie
  - Pet Songs for Esther, Rosemary & Audrey, 1952-09-09; 05-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:16:01; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Johnson, Minnie
    "[Begins with] - 'Well, I'm getting so, into a good song composer...' Then continues in Tlingit, interspersed with English: -- 'We got disgusted' -- 'I an my husband, Charley Johnson' -- 'and they said' -- 'So we got together and talked' -- 'Charley Johnson' -- 'Indian Affairs' -- 'Becky qa Beverley' (i.e. Esther's daughters) -- 'Esther du tla' (i.e. Esther's mother, Catherine Bartell) -- 'Beverly' -- 'Young' (the school teacher) -- 'Rosemary' -- 'Audrey.' Song for Esther, "Somebodda.." [at 5:48]. -- 'She stamp down' - continues explanation in Engilsh.... 'du kik Rosemary' (her yonger sister, Rosemary) -- 'when you, when she get cleaned up' -- 'I can't remember - he's working for - (tries to remember) -- 'These three little girls'. Song for Rosemary [at 13:28]. Song for Audrey [at 15:05]."
  - Hymn sung in English, Tlingit, and Tlingit Babytalk, 1952-09-09; 05-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:08:43; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Johnson, Minnie
    Children's songs; Hymns; Indians of North America--Alaska; Tlingit Indians--Alaska--Music; Tlingit language; Yakutat (Alaska)
  - Identification of recording by F de Laguna, 1952-09-09; 05-04; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:22; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004
  - Naskik's song, 1952-09-09; 06-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:11:16; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Johnson, Minnie
    "Naskik was her mother's mother's younger brother. He was chief of Reef House on Johnson Slough, and was married to a Teqwedi woman. He was the father of Situk Jim who died in 1916. He is supposed to have composed and sung this song after a quarrel with his brother-in-law, and then gone outside where he met his death. There is a hint of suicide, since in the song he wishes to join the Northern Lights, the abode of those who had died through suicide or murder."
  - The Song of the Beaver of the Kalix Kagwantan, 1952-09-13; 07-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:02:50; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Italio, Frank; Johnson, Minnie
    Beavers--Folklore; Indians of North America--Alaska; Tlingit Indians--Alaska--Music; Tlingit language; Yakutat (Alaska)
  - Story and songs of cklayaqw', 1952-09-13; 07-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:08:36; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Italio, Frank
    Indians of North America--Alaska; Quests (Expeditions); Tlingit Indians--Folklore; Tlingit language; Yakutat (Alaska)
  - Explanation of the two preceding recordings; Beaver Song and the songs attributed to cklayaqw, 1952-09-13; 07-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:17:46; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Johnson, Minnie
  - Explanation by Helen Bremner in Tlingit and English about the Beaver Song, 1952-09-13; 07-04; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:40; Bremner, Helen; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004
  - Continuation of Raven Stories: Raven's Theft of Daylight, 1952-09-13; 07-05; 1.0 .mp3; 00:27:15; De Laguna, Frederica, 1906-2004; Italio, Frank
    Completion of the story of of Raven in the box, interrupted by end of previous tape. Also includes the story of Raven in the Whale, followed without a break by Raven's Theft of Daylight, introduced by name for Dry Bay, gunaxo (i.e. among Athabaskans). The two songs given during the telling are 'Daylight' and 'I'll break it on you.' Resumption of story broken off on APSdigrec_0617.